Here, have one of these.
Fuck me.
Right.
Are you sure there's time?
There's time.
- Thank you.
Did they say how long
you'll be gone for?
No, they didn't say.
I'm very proud
they chose you, Jim.
I'll be fine.
Go.
Okay.
Morning, sir.
Sir.
Group Captain Dr. James Stagg,
chief meteorological officer,
reporting for duty.
I.D. card and pass, please, sir.
Right this way, sir.
Welcome to Southwick House, sir.
I'm Andrew Carter
with the Met Office.
I'll be your ADC.
- Mm-hmm.
I must admit it's a great honor
to meet you, Dr. Stagg.
I so enjoyed your paper
on terrestrial magnetism.
It's a fascinating subject.
It is, yes.
And here we are, sir.
Operations rooms
are upstairs, sir.
Teleprinters are in the cellars.
And our forecast room
is just through here.
- Where can I put this down?
- Anywhere, sir.
We'll have someone
take it to your tent.
What are these?
They're historical
analog charts.
I know what they are,
but what are they doing here?
Colonel Krick,
he requested them.
Well, which one is he?
Introduce me.
I believe he's with General...
Can you stop!
Stop the banging, please.
I believe
he's with General Eisenhower
at the moment, sir.
I'll call you back.
Sir.
What's coming through?
Soundings at 53 north,
35 west, sir.
Mm-hmm. Weather ship Hoste, yes?
Yes, sir.
Uh, Casey and Bryant here
are linked directly
to the teleprinter ops
at Dunstable and Bushy Park.
- Which one are you?
- I'm Casey, sir.
That's wrong, Casey.
Our American contingent, sir.
This is Flight Officer Murray,
Flight Officer Hamilton.
- Good to meet you, sir.
- They're on surface weather.
What, both of you?
Who's on upper air?
Uh, no one, sir.
No one's on upper air?
So that data just goes
unrecorded, does it?
I'll need both of you
on upper air at all times.
Uh, we were told to use
historical analog charts, sir.
Not by me.
Those weren't my instructions.
It's just, Colonel Krick
instructed us otherwise, sir.
Did he? Do I have an office?
Yes, sir.
It's just through here.
Ah.
Good afternoon, sir.
Uh, this is Group Captain Stagg.
He's just transferred
from Dunstable.
We've been very much
looking forward to his...
him joining us here.
Lieutenant Kay Summersby.
Motor Transport Corps.
Welcome to Southwick House.
Are we sharing an office,
or what?
No. I was just using it
temporarily.
Good, because I'll need it
exclusively.
Well, very good.
Can you see to it that
General Eisenhower knows
that I'm here?
And that I apologize
for my late arrival?
Yes, sir.
Sir.
Right.
Hello. Signals Department.
Switchboard speaking.
Yes, um,
Richmond 1-9-3-7, please.
I'm sorry, but all
outgoing calls are forbidden
without prior authorization,
sir.
Uh, no, no, I-I-I...
I need to speak with my wife.
- I'm sorry, sir.
- Hello?
Yes? Hello?
If you'd like to follow me,
please,
General Eisenhower
will see you now.
I wouldn't keep him waiting any
longer than you already have.
Group Captain Dr. James Stagg,
here at the express request
of General Eisenhower.
And all 265 vessels arrived
without issue, sir.
And we've assigned, uh,
five patrol craft
and three destroyers.
DWIGHT "IKE" EISENHOWER:
Let's get the job done.
Glad to hear it.
Lieutenant Summersby?
Sir, may I introduce
Group Captain James Stagg,
who finally made it in
from London?
Well, it's good to meet you,
Group Captain Stagg.
Welcome aboard.
Nice to finally put
a face to the name.
Have you got all the equipment
you need downstairs?
Equipment is not
the problem, sir.
What's the problem?
Um, well, it's time, sir.
I haven't really had any...
any time to establish
any clear picture.
Have a look, Group Captain.
I got 7,000 naval vessels,
130,000 ground troops,
200,000 naval personnel,
15 hospital ships,
8,000 doctors,
three airborne divisions
and a partridge in a pear tree.
Largest seaborne invasion force
in history.
Is it?
And do we have a date yet
for the invasion, sir?
We invade France Monday.
- This Monday?
- Correct.
Monday, June 5th, 0630.
That is D-Day,
which is in 61 hours from now.
Fate of the war hinges on this.
All the pieces of the jigsaw
are in place.
There's only one imponderable
that remains.
I need a forecast.
I'm... Yes, I'm concerned
that what you're asking me is
scientifically impossible, sir.
Uh, long-term forecasting is
really only ever
educated guesswork.
Monday is not long-term,
for Christ's sake.
Does Monday sound like long-term
to you, Lieutenant Summersby?
No, it certainly does not, sir.
Well, this is
Northern Europe, sir.
Anything over 24 hours is-is...
is considered long-term,
meteorologically speaking.
But I'll...
I'll do my best.
I don't want your best.
I already expect that.
I need certainty.
Churchill tells me
you're the best meteorologist
in the country
and that I should rely on you
over Colonel Krick.
You know him?
Only by reputation.
Well, Krick's been with me
since '42.
He's never steered me wrong,
so...
let's see how you measure up.
I need a forecast for Monday.
I need it first thing
tomorrow morning.
Y-Yes, sir.
Don't let me down.
Group Captain.
Let's go.
♪ He had a boogie style
that no one else could play ♪
♪ He was the top man
at his craft ♪
♪ But then his number came up ♪
♪ And he was gone
with the draft ♪
♪ He's in the Army now
a-blowing reveille ♪
♪ He's the boogie-woogie
bugle boy of Company B ♪
♪ They made him blow a bugle
for his Uncle Sam ♪
♪ It really brought him down
because he couldn't jam ♪
♪ The captain seemed
to understand ♪
♪ Because the next day
the cap went out ♪
- ♪ And drafted a band ♪
- Kay!
♪ And now the company jumps... ♪
Ladies and gentlemen,
Kay Summersby. Take over.
- Come on, Kay.
- Oh.
- Dance with me.
Like old times.
There you go.
- There you go.
Oh, stick to piano, Irv.
I-I don't believe you've met,
uh, Group Captain Stagg.
Only by telephone.
Dr. Stagg, so nice
to finally meet you.
You're younger than I imagined.
You're shorter than I imagined.
Analogs.
I realize that, yes.
Every single weather chart
for Northern Europe since 1900.
Mm. Um, in my experience,
the weather never replicates
its own history.
Ah, well, try telling that
to a movie producer.
Remember Selznick, Kay?
Oh.
July '39.
David Selznick calls me up.
He's making a movie.
He wants a forecast
for a three-day period
in Beverly Hills.
- The scene is...
the burning of Atlanta.
"I don't want to see
a drop of rain, Irv.
Not a drop. Not a drop."
Well, MGM calls me up.
They give me the dates.
I give 'em the forecast.
Beautiful weather.
I mean, just gorgeous.
Not a cloud in the sky.
Movie's a hit.
I get to meet Clark Gable.
Little picture— I-I don't know
if you heard of it.
Called Gone with the Wind.
- You seen it, Stagg?
- No.
No? That...
That's crazy. Who hasn't seen
Gone with the Wind?
Me. I haven't seen it.
Well, you must.
I mean, it's a great picture.
It's great. I saw it with Ike.
Kay drove us...
to the London premiere.
- This is true.
- Great night.
So, did you meet Vivien Leigh?
Oh, we sure did.
- What was she like?
Uh, she was cute.
The Allied High Command
has requested
our forecast
by 1:00 p.m. tomorrow.
Time and date of the invasion
to France
has been confirmed for Monday.
Monday. Monday.
June 5th, 6:30 a.m.,
so can we start, please?
Get rid of the piano. Thank you.
Is it bothering you, Dr. Stagg?
- It's inappropriate.
Call this extension
if you need to speak
to General Eisenhower anytime,
day or night.
Is this his direct line?
Oh, no.
It's a direct line to me.
I handle all communication
with the general.
Can I have your attention,
please?
Bryant, can you put
the phone down, please?
Is that his name? Bryant?
Okay, go ahead.
I needn't, I hope,
have to stress to you
how crucial this forecast is,
but I do want to stress
one thing to you all
and one thing only:
Get me the data.
That's what counts.
Get me the latest readings
from every single base
within 2,000 miles of Normandy.
That's Paris, Galway, Reykjavík,
Boston, Washington, Lisbon...
New York, Newfoundland.
You get the idea.
Get me the data
from every Met station,
every weather balloon,
every reconnaissance flight.
That's upper air.
That's surface air.
That's radar soundings.
That's sea temperature.
That's salinity. Everything.
If we've measured it,
then I want it.
That room there...
that's where I'll be.
Get me the data.
That's what counts.
700 millibars.
210. 28.
650 millibars.
- Plus 19.
Observations
coming in from Spain.
Sea surface temp: 18 degrees.
Ten-tenths
stratocumulus and altocumulus
now rising in zero-two.
1-0-1-5 millibars.
Northwest wind, force five.
6-0-0 millibars.
Wind southwest, force four.
South Iceland
seven-tenths, 30,000 feet.
Southeast, force six.
1-0-1-8 millibars.
Say that again, please.
Repeat that.
- Are you getting the
I front temp? -No, I have...
Seven-tenths, stratocumulus,
3,000 feet, force six.
Southwesterly, force six.
We're still waiting on
the Greenland data, sir.
Just-just leave that.
Just leave that be.
What speed is L3 moving at?
25 knots.
- Finished with that?
Ten StratoCu 3,000 feet,
southeast, force four.
1-0-1-3 millibars.
Radar soundings from 0930.
There's been no movement
from the main course.
Sir, the weather conditions
in Normandy.
These are from yesterday's
12 o'clock, sir.
Humidity reports.
And we have those folders
you requested...
There's nothing there.
Carter. It's done.
Good man.
Sir.
The latest completed maps.
Oh, come on.
Look at the analogs.
It's as plain as day:
calm, sunny weather.
Those analogs prove
absolutely nothing.
How can you say that?
It's right here.
- Are you blind?
Look at it.
I don't need to look at it.
The chart is 19 years old.
Fine, that's-that's
40 years old,
27 years, uh, 15 years old.
That's-that's the point:
patterns over time.
Okay. Thank you.
I think what we need to do
is establish
what we already know today,
here and now.
Um, we have
two aggressive storms
stretching themselves
across the Atlantic
from Newfoundland to Normandy.
Agreed.
There is an area of
high pressure above the Azores.
That's what interests me.
But it's moving lethargically
and...
Your word, not mine.
I'm sorry, would you like
the floor again?
Me? No, it's your floor.
Go ahead.
We can't just base the forecast
on surface air
and, uh, analog charts.
We must also consider
the jet stream, which...
The jet stream?
Yes, the jet stream
currently hurtling its way
towards Europe
and dragging
both the storms with it,
likely spawning a third storm.
That jet stream.
Okay.
Which will inevitably mean
stormier conditions
over the next few days—
tomorrow, Sunday, into Monday.
Disastrous conditions
for an invasion.
Okay, thank you so much,
Dr. Stagg.
Now, this is a chart
for June 2, 1925.
Nearly identical conditions
to today.
Same depressions
in the Atlantic,
same high pressures
over the Azores.
Move ahead... three days
to June 5, 1925,
D-Day if you will.
Calm. Sunny weather.
1925 is entirely irrelevant
to what we're talking about.
I could've just as easily picked
June 2, 1904, or 1929.
You know as well as I do
that atmospheric conditions
can never be identical ever.
What I do know is who nailed
the forecast at Alamein
for the Western Desert campaign,
for the Tunisian campaign,
for Operation Torch.
I know who got it right
every goddamn time in Cairo.
In Tripoli, Algiers,
Oran, Casablanca.
Do you know?
You?
Yeah. Me.
This isn't Casablanca,
Colonel Krick.
This is Northern Europe.
It doesn't matter.
When the atmospheric conditions
are a match,
the weather follows suit.
Mark my words.
D-Day will be calm and sunny.
Nighty night, gentlemen.
Nobody move.
Back to work.
What do you make of Stagg?
Hmm.
Scottish.
Churchill says he's a genius.
Hmm.
Yeah, well...
men are too fond of that word.
Three-tenths Cu and StratoCu
at 2,000 feet,
cloud extending to West Wales.
Inflatable Shermans,
Spitfires, Long Toms
and troop carriers.
Just rubber and air, gentlemen.
But to a Nazi
reconnaissance plane,
utterly indistinguishable
from the real thing.
In North Africa,
I proved this time and again
with victory after victory
after victory.
Of course, it's not just about
crushing the enemy, gentlemen.
It's about deceiving him, too,
and deceive him we will.
We've conjured up phantom armies
across all of East Anglia,
thousands of fake supply depots,
false radio transmissions,
empty tents
and decoy campfires.
On D-Day,
dummy paratroopers
weighted with sand
will be dropped 15 to 20 miles
inland from the Normandy coast.
They explode on impact.
Only the chute remains.
With any luck, the enemy will
think our boys are running wild
through the French interior,
drawing great chunks
of their forces
right away from the beaches.
It's a little small,
don't you think, Monty?
Small?
It's a joke, Monty.
Yes.
What's small is our window.
The 12th SS Panzer
is already near Caen.
The 352nd Infantry Division
are heavily entrenched.
If we delay beyond Monday,
they will see right through
all of this.
Everything that we have done,
all our meticulous efforts,
will be for naught.
He's doubled his defenses
in as many weeks.
Every passing hour
makes our task more perilous.
Ideally, we bring D-Day forward.
Can't be done.
We are two days out.
The more prepared the enemy,
the more ruthless I must become.
Though it's not my wish,
if it means getting
more men ashore,
I may have to sacrifice
every last member
of my advance brigade.
Well, if I didn't
know you better, Monty,
I would've thought
you enjoyed saying that.
Yes.
But then again,
I've actually been to war.
Be that as it may,
you're the boss.
I am.
And the final decision on the
timing of D-Day will be mine...
and mine alone.
Pray for good weather.
The weather is irrelevant.
We must go,
whatever the weather.
George said that
she came over to him.
She came over to him, right?
Ah.
Thought I'd pop in
and identify myself.
Bernard Montgomery.
Oh, yes.
Hello. Uh, James Stagg.
All looking good for Monday?
Um, no.
No, no, no.
Can't say that we are, sir.
Well, can't be that bad, surely.
Well, you know
this country, sir.
Looks can be deceiving.
Hmm.
Do not sow doubt, Group Captain.
Battles are lost
when doubt enters the mind.
We'll cross the Channel
on Monday.
That is definite.
If D-Day is canceled,
we will lose this war.
Do you want to be
personally responsible
for losing this war,
Group Captain Stagg?
No, sir.
For Christ's sake.
Okay.
We ready to go?
Go where?
To the meeting.
And when we get to the meeting,
what will we be saying exactly?
Monday will be calm and sunny.
The barometer at Foynes
has been falling all morning.
Yeah, I saw it.
Minimal drop, insignificant.
I think it's significant.
Listen, pal.
I've been working with Ike
for three years.
- I know the guy.
- Mm-hmm. And?
He won't want uncertainty.
Right. Well, then I better
attend the meeting alone.
Are you kidding?
You can't do that.
That's not how that works.
Uh, you can't do that.
The responsibility for
the D-Day forecast is mine,
and it's not one that
I'm going to take lightly.
It's not yours.
Okay? It's ours.
Ours, jointly.
No, no. There's one
chief meteorological officer,
and it's not you.
You won't be attending
the meeting.
Is there anything else?
Asshole.
Irv.
- How much time do I have?
- It's time.
What happened
with Colonel Krick?
Never mind Colonel Krick.
Well, they won't like this.
Well, I don't like this.
They're waiting for you,
Group Captain Stagg.
- Yes?
- Sir, he's here.
Excuse me, gentlemen.
Group Captain Stagg.
This is
General Bernard Montgomery,
commander in chief,
Allied land forces.
And here we have
Air Chief Marshal Leigh-Mallory,
commander in chief,
Allied Expeditionary Air Force.
This is Admiral Ramsay,
commander in chief,
Allied naval forces,
and Lieutenant General
Omar Bradley,
commander of
the U.S. First Army.
Where's Colonel Krick?
He's not attending, sir.
Why not?
Well, I believe it's my duty
to brief you all
on the forecast for Monday.
- He should be here.
- Shall I have him fetched?
My forecast will be the same
whether Colonel Krick
attends or not.
All right.
Going forward, I want him here.
Is that understood?
- Certainly, sir.
- Good.
What have you got?
Regrettably, we are faced
with a succession
of two aggressive storms
in the Atlantic
of unprecedented intensity
for this time of year.
My forecast, therefore...
Uh, excuse me.
My forecast, therefore,
for Monday, June 5th,
the proposed D-Day,
is as follows.
Wind, west-northwest, strong,
reaching force six,
possibly force seven.
Force seven? Are you sure?
No.
It's an estimate.
Cloud low.
Visibility poor.
Rain very likely.
Waves eight to 12 feet,
possibly with an increase
to 15 feet.
Confidence... poor.
Monday, June 5th
through at least
Tuesday, June 6th, falling...
to very poor.
Stagg, I-I'm no weatherman,
but have you looked
out a window lately?
Well, the weather
in this part of Europe, sir,
can change very rapidly.
This poor visibility— how poor?
Less than a mile,
or thereabouts.
Our paratroopers
require a full moon
to land on target.
Spring tides are essential
for landing our watercraft.
Do you realize,
Group Captain Stagg,
that Monday, June 5th is
the only date this calendar year
upon which these conditions
perfectly coincide?
I do realize. Of course, sir.
So, when exactly
do you suggest we go?
Well, as it relates
to the weather,
it's impossible to say.
As to the moon and the tides,
the next opportunity
would be June 18.
Two more weeks? Are you mad?
We can't keep our preparations
secret for that long.
It's just not possible.
Of course it isn't.
The enemy will be ready
and waiting.
They'll slaughter
every single last one of us.
That's an extremely
pessimistic forecast.
Are you absolutely certain?
No.
I'm not certain.
I'm confident
that the storms will come.
I can't be absolutely certain
as to when.
Not good enough.
If the storms come tonight,
then they may burn
themselves off by Monday.
If they come tomorrow,
then the weather will be...
exactly as I described.
We must go regardless.
This moment demands judgment
shaped by
actual battlefield experience.
We can't risk another
Exercise Tiger.
My men are ready and primed
for the big match.
Get them onto the beaches
somehow, anyhow.
Leave the rest to me.
Reload me, please.
Let's go. It's time.
Monty.
You can think what you like,
and you can say what you like
to my face,
but don't you ever undermine me
in front of the men again.
Relax, old chap.
It's not as if
I'm telling them anything
they don't already know.
Tiger was a training op.
Dress rehearsal for D-Day.
Half those boys were
fresh out of the draft.
So I called in
live artillery to...
toughen them up.
Naval command was
supposed to bomb the beach
an hour before we landed.
There were delays, so we had to
push the start time back.
Our radios had a different
frequency from the Brits.
Our boys never got the message.
They walked right into it.
One mistake.
Just that one mistake.
Ike.
Ike, look at me.
You have to stop doing this
to yourself.
What's done is done.
When I close my eyes...
all I can see is failure.
Well, look what the cat
dragged in.
Evening, sir.
Evening, Irv.
You doing all right?
Yeah. Can we talk?
What's on your mind?
Well, sir, I'm not sure
- if you're aware of...
- Ike!
Associated Press
have just announced
that we're landing
in France tomorrow.
CBS, Radio Moscow,
they've already picked it up.
- Get General McClure on this.
- Yep.
I want this cleaned up now.
And I want names.
Understood.
You were saying?
Stagg!
- Stagg!
Everyone out!
Move!
Close the door behind you.
That, uh, forecast you gave...
was that the view
of the British
and the American teams?
It was the view of
the Allied Meteorological Unit.
Don't give me
that mealymouthed crap!
Krick told me—
he just told me!--
the weather on Monday
is gonna be fine.
Just fine. Sunny and beautiful!
Well, Colonel Krick had no right
to speak on behalf of...
Wrong!
Colonel Krick has every right
to speak up if he thinks
that that will affect
the outcome of the invasion!
Is that clear?
Is it?
Yes, sir.
Who do you think
you are, anyway?
Who?
Ordering my man to stand down?
Pestering my staff
so that you can phone home?
May I respond, sir?
I'm all ears.
As chief meteorological officer,
I take full responsibility
for the recommendation made
at the meeting.
And it was precisely because
Colonel Krick and I disagreed
that I decided it would be
clearer and simpler
if I spoke alone.
Krick's forecasts have saved
thousands of lives.
Why on God's green earth
should I trust you?
Because Colonel Krick
has been lucky.
Good.
I like luck.
Why was he lucky?
He's been lucky because
he's been tasked
with forecasting
stable weather systems.
When patterns are predictable,
then yes, of course,
analog charts can be useful.
In North Africa,
he never made a mistake.
- Not once.
- Well, of course he didn't.
He was safe as houses there.
The conditions here, sir...
they're not comparable.
Look at the charts, sir.
Here, there are two—
not one but two—
major storms advancing towards
the Normandy coast
even as we speak.
That's nowhere near France.
No, sir.
Not yet.
I want a forecast
the two of you agree on.
Clear?
Yes, sir.
OPW confirmed full retraction.
Thank you.
Not at all, sir.
I didn't tell him about
you trying to call home.
Someone downstairs must have
leaked it, I'm afraid.
Okay.
He gets like that sometimes.
Just let it wash over you.
He won't even remember
what he said.
That how you deal with him?
Ah, he's nothing.
I was an ambulance driver
during the Blitz.
There were so many dead bodies,
we had to use a cinema
as a morgue.
- You just grow a thick skin.
- Hmm.
From ambulance driver
to aide
to the supreme commander.
Mm-hmm.
Driver, secretary,
aide, nurse.
Everything, really.
We've been together
for three years now.
I've been to Morocco, Algeria.
Must be exciting.
It has its moments.
So, these storms
you keep talking about—
how are you so certain
that they're coming?
I'm not certain.
You can't be certain
about the weather.
All we can do is
look to the evidence.
Do you know that weathermen are
traditionally a little boring?
- How dare you say that?
Weathermen, maybe, but how can
the weather be boring?
It feeds us.
The weather.
Can destroy us.
Controls our daily life.
I don't think that's boring.
People ask, "When will it rain?
When will the sun come out?"
But what about,
"Why does it rain?"
"Why does the wind blow?"
"What's the wind?"
Excuse me.
Yes. Stagg.
Yes, go ahead. Repeat that.
Zero, zero, one, zero, four...
StratoCu at 2,000 feet.
Tops at 5,000 feet.
Good news or bad?
We're looking good, sir.
I couldn't disagree
with that more.
We're not looking good at all.
You know what, I am done
with this Scotch pessimism
of yours, this Highland gloom.
I'm not from the Highlands.
Well, your Lowland gloom, then.
I'm neither from the Highlands
nor the Lowlands.
Well, wherever it is he's from,
we're in good shape
for Monday, sir.
You see this?
This ridge of high pressure
has already moved in
from the Azores,
just as it did on June 3, 1925.
This is moronic.
This is actually moronic.
Oh, so I'm moronic now?
That's great, Stagg.
That's just great.
Just insult me right to my face.
I'm not insulting you.
I'm just describing you.
As a moron?
All right, enough.
As a confident moron, yes.
Oh, go to hell, Stagg.
You come in here,
- you think you're better
than us? -Hey! All right,
all right, all right,
that's enough.
Jesus Christ.
We have three hours.
Three hours until we
take this up with the C-in-Cs.
Now...
go or not go?
Sir, what we need to consider...
No, no. No, no more considering.
No.
Go or don't go? Go or don't go?
- That's it. Which is it?
We should go, sir.
Stagg.
I'm sorry,
we'll have to call you back.
Understood.
Uh, uh, I-I'm sorry, sir.
It's for you.
Not now.
They say it's extremely urgent.
Yes. Stagg.
Sir, this is
Private Amy Haig from Signals
relaying a message from
the Dunstable Met Office.
Your wife was taken to the
maternity ward of St. Mary's.
- She is pregnant, yes?
- Yes.
Yes, that's correct.
Is the baby here?
Have I missed it?
Well, sir,
they felt you should know:
St. Mary's Hospital was bombed
earlier tonight.
There have been casualties,
sir, and they're...
they're still looking
for your wife.
Group Captain Stagg?
Is there any more information?
Not at this point, sir.
But there's been casualties?
Yes, sir.
Okay. Well, um...
Well, if you have any more...
information,
then let me know— anything.
Of course, sir.
Thank you.
You're welcome, sir.
There a problem, Stagg?
No. It's irrelevant.
Good.
So, can I give the order?
What?
The order.
For Monday.
No.
N-No?
I mean, so you're saying
don't give the order?
Is that it?
Yeah, that... Yes.
Yes. I'm saying that...
I'm saying...
that the weather on Monday
will be extremely poor.
Let me tell you
my problem, Stagg.
Even I can see that
Krick's anticyclone
is on the move,
because it's right here
on the goddamn map.
Now, our final meeting
is at 0400 hours,
and that will be
the absolute last opportunity
to change anything,
so unless you can prove
these storms are inbound,
we invade as planned
Monday, June 5th, 0630 hours.
Yes, sir.
Three hours, gentlemen.
You ready? You ready?
- Yeah!
♪ Oh... ♪
♪ The hi-de-ho man, that's me ♪
♪ How'd you like
to blow your top? ♪
♪ Dig yourself
some fine rebop? ♪
♪ Hi-de-hi, he-de-he ♪
♪ Oh, the hi-de-ho man,
that's me ♪
♪ Hi-de, hi-de, hi-de-hi ♪
♪ Hi-de, hi-de,
hi-de-hi ♪
♪ Hey-de, hey-de, hey-de-hey ♪
♪ Hey-de, hey-de,
hey-de-hey ♪
♪ He-de, he-de, he-de-he ♪
♪ He-de, he-de,
he-de-he ♪
♪ Hi-de, hi-de, hi-de-hi ♪
♪ Hi-de, hi-de,
hi-de-hi ♪
♪ Say, I hepped 'em in London ♪
♪ I hepped 'em in Holland ♪
♪ I hepped 'em in gay Paris ♪
♪ Yes, sirree, yes, sirree ♪
♪ Oh, the hi-de-ho man,
that's me ♪
♪ Hi-de, hi-de, hi-de-hi ♪
♪ Hi-de, hi-de-hi ♪
♪ Oh-ho, de-ho-de ♪
♪ Ho, de-ho-de ♪
♪ Hi-de, hi-de, hi-de-hi ♪
♪ Hi-de, hi-de,
hi-de-hi ♪
♪ The hi-de-ho man, that's me. ♪
- Dr. Stagg.
Come with me.
Come on.
We need you back there.
You'll be all right.
- Yes.
- Mm-hmm.
Anything at all.
Yeah.
Uh, this just came through, sir.
I want to say something.
Yeah, what's that?
I think the way
you're treating Stagg is wrong.
I think if you keep it up,
he's gonna crack
and you'll lose him.
Then I'll work with Krick.
You know I like Irv,
but he-he's no match for Stagg.
Since when are you an expert?
Don't talk to me like that.
His wife is in the hospital.
- She's pregnant.
- In labor.
Hospital's bombed, yes.
I know. What else?
He doesn't know if his
pregnant wife is dead or alive.
Uh-huh. Yes.
- Let me find out.
- Find out what?
I can make it to the hospital
and back in a couple of hours.
- How are you gonna do that?
- It'll give him clarity.
No. No, I need you here.
It's just a couple of hours.
No.
Dismissed.
Dismissed, Lieutenant.
South Iceland,
seven-tenths StratoCu,
3,000 feet,
- southeast force six.
ten-tenths at 1,500 feet.
So we have warm sector
conditions over Ireland,
and low 9-9-6 is off
the northwest of Scotland.
It's the secondary low.
That's causing a low cloud base.
It's very high dew points
in that warm sector upstream.
No sign of frontal systems
moving north.
Not yet.
- They're about to start, sir.
- Just a couple more minutes.
Please.
I have the 1300 and 1800
surface air maps. Bryant.
It's okay.
We don't need the charts.
We still have
a little time, sir.
Irving, why don't you
start us off, please?
Yes, sir.
Gentlemen...
this is a chart
for June 3, 1925.
You'll notice here and here
a temporary weakening
of pressure over the Azores,
just as we're seeing today.
Now, within 24 hours,
that pressure reasserted itself,
and it cleared the storm
threatening Northern Europe.
As you can see...
nearly identical patterns
occurred in 1904 and 1925,
and I can give you
plenty of others,
but the bottom line is this:
Tomorrow, Monday, June 5th,
is good to go.
Thank you.
Stagg?
You've got the floor.
Nobody here likes me very much.
I realize that,
and that's all right.
I don't expect you to like me,
but I do want you
to listen to me.
Um, I could stand here
and provide you
with yet more, uh, data—
the latest barometric readings,
the wind speeds,
the new upper-air soundings
that we've collated—
but none of it is going to make
a lick of difference, is it?
Is it?
Because you want
to believe that—
what Colonel Krick's just said,
that it's going to be safe
to land in Normandy tomorrow—
and so that's what you believe.
But everything
that he's just said
is pure, unadulterated...
horseshit.
You can muster
all the tanks and soldiers
and ships that you like.
You can assemble the greatest
armada that ever there was,
but if you invade tomorrow,
they're going to be washed away.
Because the storms that
I'm talking about are real,
and the jet stream
that's propelling them
towards the Normandy coast
is real,
and the wrath of nature...
is real.
And if you ignore it,
then countless men
and countless boys...
That's it.
He's lost his bloody mind.
Why is it horseshit?
Yes, the weather was
as he described
in 1904 and 1925,
but he fails to mention 1916.
June 5th,
the Battle for Mount Sorrel.
Then, as now, there were
areas of high pressure
above the Azores,
but the storms came anyway.
Many people here will remember
that battle.
Chaos. Absolute chaos!
Thousands of lives lost!
Hell on earth! Torrential rain!
He's selecting the data
that suits him
and ignoring the rest,
and we must face the facts.
The facts!
However frightening they may be!
Well, if...
if not Monday, when?
Not before June 18.
Christ on a bike, he's still
talking about the 18th.
- The 18th?
There is no 18th.
No 18th. No 18th!
None!
None, none, none, none, none!
The 18th is not an option!
Montgomery.
Bertie...
what is the worst
we can tolerate?
Waves of four to six feet
would be tolerable.
Anything over six feet...
impossible.
Stagg?
I'm estimating waves
of eight to ten feet.
Trafford, worst case?
Cloud base can't be lower
than a thousand feet,
or we're flying blind.
Cloud base will be
at least eight to ten-tenths
below a thousand feet.
Then don't fly.
Ramsay, you get us ashore,
our men will handle the rest.
- Without air cover?
- With or without.
Shut up, Monty.
We need to land,
is what we need to do.
If we don't land,
we have no fourth front,
- and without a fourth front...
- For God's sake, Monty.
With waves of ten feet,
we won't be landing anywhere.
Well, then, let's just start
the blasted Kraut lessons now,
then, shall we,
and all the goose-stepping?
And then maybe one day
years from now,
we can all yodel about
the time that we didn't...
- Enough!
Krick, do you have
anything to add?
I'm telling you, sir, next week
is nothing but clear skies.
If you choose to postpone,
you'll regret it
for the rest of your lives.
I maintain my position.
And I maintain mine.
Then so be it.
D-Day will be postponed.
Ike.
I hate to bring this up,
but we have hundreds
of thousands of troops
ready to deploy down there.
Now, they've obviously
been briefed
as to the invasion plans.
Yeah,
that's a lot of loose lips.
- Secure all troops.
- I repeat, secure all troops.
- I repeat,
all troops must be
detained at once.
No one leaves
until further notice.
I repeat, all troops
must be detained at once.
All troops must be
detained at once.
Secure them on board,
no exceptions.
You did the right thing.
Jesus.
Should've gone.
Ike.
♪ All creatures
of our God and King ♪
♪ Lift up
your voice and with us sing ♪
♪ Alleluia, alleluia ♪
♪ Thou burning sun ♪
♪ With golden beam ♪
♪ Thou silver moon ♪
♪ With softer gleam ♪
♪ O praise him, O praise him ♪
♪ Alleluia, alleluia ♪
♪ Alleluia ♪
♪ Thou rushing wind
that art so strong ♪
♪ Ye clouds that sail
in heaven along ♪
♪ O praise him, O praise him ♪
♪ Alleluia, alleluia ♪
♪ Alleluia. ♪
God, grant to the living...
grace.
To the departed, rest.
To the nation,
peace and concord.
To us all, your servants,
the promise of eternal life.
Your blessing to unite us all
in your service
to our God
and to this, our country.
- Light to guide us...
guide us on our way.
Courage to support us
and your blessing to unite us...
- in service to you.
Amen.
We can't keep the men
locked up like this, Ike.
Not for two more weeks.
Well, what do you want me to do?
Furlough 300,000 men
with the playbook for D-Day?
We might as well
tell the Nazis ourselves.
It's just an observation.
We will find a way, Trafford.
Hang in there.
Yes.
Sir.
So L2 and 3
have merged into one system.
Mm. And a new low
has intensified
east of Newfoundland.
Uh, sir?
Excuse me, Dr. Stagg?
The cold front appears to be
clearing western Ireland.
What?
It's clearing, sir.
What's the geostrophic gradient?
Uh, 40 knots north, sir.
So it's slowing.
Well, you can't be sure, sir.
We've only had one reading.
- Where'd it come from?
- Northwest Ireland.
Tell me specifically,
who... who recorded it?
What weather base?
A Miss Maureen Sweeney, sir.
- Blacksod Point.
- Show me.
Well, call her back.
Double-check it.
- Triple-check it.
- Sir.
Right now, please.
Can you ask, uh, Teleprinter Ops
to get me readings
from every base
within 500 miles
of Blacksod Point? Right now.
Can I get the latest
climate readings, please?
Yeah?
Um...
This just came in
from Blacksod Point.
Was it checked?
They're checking it now.
Could mean something,
could mean nothing.
Yes, but which?
What do you think?
Why are you asking me?
Look out the goddamn window,
Stagg.
I'm asking you because
I need your expertise.
Please.
It's the fifth reading.
It is unusual.
Mm-hmm. Yeah, it is.
It's worth looking into.
Good.
Heavy frontal cloud, west of 35.
Blacksod Point
barometer fell overnight,
then slight rise by afternoon,
front offshore.
1-0-1-1 millibars.
Who do you got now?
Who are you speaking with?
I was just asking him about...
So, what are you doing now?
And get the result
for that one, please.
The low is moving
in the right direction, but...
- It's too close.
- Yeah.
Hamilton, when's the next chart
coming out?
Within the hour, sir.
Within the hour
is not good enough.
Can we get...
can we get Dunstable...
a result from Dun-Dunstable in,
please, soon?
It should've been with us
an hour ago.
What's the movement
on the cold front?
Still 30 knots, sir.
Have you ever seen
a progression like this?
Never. Winter, maybe.
Never this time of year.
StratoCu
lifting above 2,000 feet.
Sea surface
temperature, 15 degrees.
Data points up
to 400 millibars.
What are you looking for?
A gap,
because there's one there.
You call that a gap?
Yes, I call that a gap.
That's a very narrow gap.
A narrow gap is still a gap.
Thank you.
Do you see a gap?
I believe there's one
forming, sir, yes.
Yes, a gap. Thank you.
So, if this was a normal
forecast, would you call it?
Yeah.
I don't know. Uh, probably.
The only difference is
it's D-Day.
Big difference.
Call Eisenhower.
You wanted to see me?
Yes, sir.
There's been a development, sir.
It seems the storm
at Newfoundland is slowing.
We believe it's enough
to provide a... a...
a window
in the disruptive weather.
Um...
Well, if I may,
th-the cigarettes
are the Newfoundland storm,
the larger one of three.
My glasses here are
the two smaller storms.
Currently, the larger storm is
dragging the two smaller storms
away from the Normandy coast,
leaving a...
a gap in the weather of sorts
just long enough for us to land
in Normandy on Tuesday morning.
Tuesday?
As in 26 hours from now,
Sir, if you just look
at the latest charts...
I don't want to look
at your damn charts.
It's a bunch of gobbledygook.
What I want is for you
to get down on your knees
and look me in the eye
and tell me,
"Tuesday morning, sir,
the sun's got his hat on."
Because in case
you haven't noticed,
there's a goddamn hurricane
blowing out there!
Technically, it's not
a hurricane, sir.
Sunny weather, you say stop.
Hurricane, you say go.
Well, no. Well, yes, sir.
Yes, that's exactly
what I'm saying.
Send my men into...
into the storm?
Yeah.
They'll never see it coming,
sir, never.
A gap like this
in the storm— never.
You're absolutely sure of that?
Are you absolutely sure
about that, Group Captain Stagg?
I'm sure there'll be a gap.
The weather won't be perfect...
but it'll do.
This is your official position?
My official position is this.
Go.
You should go, sir.
Okay, we'll go.
D-Day is Tuesday, June 6.
- This is my statement...
- if all goes well tomorrow.
- Mm-hmm.
And...
this one if not.
- Hey.
- Hmm?
I've got a surprise for you.
Rare as nylons.
I have a good feeling
about tomorrow.
- You should get some sleep.
- Yes.
Yeah?
- 0630 hours.
My men did all that bravery
and devotion to duty could do.
If any blame or fault
is attached to the attempt,
it is mine and mine alone.
That's what I wrote.
In case we fail tomorrow.
We won't.
Soldiers, sailors and airmen
of the Allied
Expeditionary Force...
you are about to embark
upon the Great Crusade,
upon which we have striven
these many months.
The eyes of the world
are upon you.
The hope and prayers
of liberty-loving people
everywhere march with you.
In company with our brave allies
and brothers-in-arms
on other fronts,
you will bring about
the destruction
of the German war machine...
the elimination
of Nazi tyranny
over the oppressed peoples
of Europe
and security for ourselves
in a free world.
You get any sleep?
Not a wink.
You?
Nope.
Your task
will not be an easy one.
Your enemy is well trained,
well equipped
and battle-hardened.
He will fight savagely.
60 seconds to H hour.
Radio silence ends in...
60 seconds.
But this is the year 1944.
Where you from?
Bracken Mountain,
North Carolina, sir.
- Bracken Mountain,
North Carolina? -Yes, sir.
The tide has turned.
The free men of the world
are marching together
to victory.
What's your name?
- Uh, Oiler, sir.
- Oiler. Where you from, Oiler?
I have full confidence in
your courage, devotion to duty
and skill in battle.
We will accept nothing less
than full victory.
Good luck,
and let us beseech the blessing
of Almighty God
upon this great
and noble undertaking.
Utah. Come in, Utah.
Utah, come in.
SHAEF main to Utah.
Come in, Utah.
Omaha Beach
control, do you read?
Utah, come in.
Utah, do you read?
Utah... hit by
machine-gun fire. Casualties...
Heavy incoming fire
at Utah Beach.
What about the other beaches?
Serious
casualties at Omaha Beach.
How many casualties?
Westerly winds
causing course corrections.
Visibility two miles,
ceiling falling to 1,500 feet.
Landing craft
swept off course at Utah.
Visibility two miles.
Ceiling falling to 1,500 feet.
Omaha sky still overcast...
unable to locate batteries
lying on south beach.
- Keep moving!
- Keep pushing!
Move! Move!
Incoming! Take cover!
Cannot
unload due to heavy shellfire.
L1 section lost in water.
Second half moving forward.
800 yards off the beach.
Omaha winds 14 knots west.
Taking heavy fire
at Gold and Omaha.
Many wounded at Dog Red,
needing immediate evacuation.
Cloud
ceiling low, around 500 feet.
Cloud ceiling
low, around 500 feet.
... find no targets
of opportunity...
Can find
no targets of opportunity
without endangering own landing.
We can't see a bloody thing!
Wind 18 knots, west, southwest.
Wind 18 knots,
west, southwest.
Clouds 800 feet,
beginning to rise.
- You're good. You're good.
- Am I gonna die?
No, we'll get you home.
You're good. You're good.
Waves moderating
at Utah, now two to three feet.
Ceiling lifting to 1,500 feet.
Clearer skies inland.
Keep pushing!
- I don't care! Go!
Utah cloud ceiling clear.
Move up!
Two U.S. destroyers
are within one...
Move up!
Yes?
Mm-hmm.
What?
Thank you.
Footholds established
on all the beaches.
Our men are ashore,
with full air and naval support.
Hello. Signals Department.
Yes, St. Mary's Hospital
in Clapham, please.
I'm sorry, sir, but there are
still no outgoing calls
until security restrictions
have been officially lifted.
- I believe...
I've arranged a car to take you
straight to the hospital.
Thank you very much.
I appreciate that.
Well, congratulations, Stagg.
Congratulations to you, too.
Good luck.
Thank you so much
for everything.
Ah, don't be silly.
I'm sorry I couldn't
have done more.
No, no, no.
We were busy.
Thank you.
No, no. You can't.
No! No!
Hello, Jim.
Hello, Liz.
Are you all right?
You okay?
Yeah?
Your son.
Oh.
Hello.
Hello, beautiful.